Guide to the Joe J. Locati papers 1880-1998
Whitman College and Northwest Archives
Joe J. Locati papers
1880-1998
Whitman College and Northwest Archives 345 Boyer Avenue Walla Walla, WA 99362 Archives@whitman.edu https://library.whitman.edu/archives/
Locati, Joe J.
WCMss.044
1.4 linear feet 2 boxes
This collection includes research materials of Joe Locati, an inspector with the United States Department of Agriculture, including photographs and newspaper articles related to agriculture in Walla Walla and the history of Italian Jesuits in the Northwest.
Collection is open for research.
Donated to the Whitman College and Northwest Archives by Joe J. Locati between 1979 and 1995. The accession number is retro-0440.
Joe J. Locati was born in 1908, the fourth son of Milanese immigrants. He was the first member of his family to attend high school. After graduating, he enrolled in business school but eventually turned to gardening. His first job with the Walla Walla Gardener's Association eventually led him to become an inspector for the Washington State Department of Agriculture.
In 1978, after his retirement, he wrote The Horticultural Heritage of Walla Walla County, 1818-1977. It has become a well-known resource for area growers and historians. He also penned a manuscript titled, "Walla Walla Sweet Onion: The French Connection." Locati died in 1998.
This collection holds photographs, newspaper articles, and other research materials Locati used in compiling his work on Walla Walla County's horticultural history, a series of articles on the history of Italian Jesuits in the Northwest, and two scrapbooks containing newspaper clippings regarding horticultural practices in Walla Walla, 1918-1981.
Agriculture
- Research materials for The Horticultural Heritage of Walla Walla County, 1818-1977: Photocopied pictures, notes, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Photo: Picking apples, Baker Langdon Orchard, circa 1919-1920 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Photo: Interior Baker-Langdon apple packing house, circa 1920 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Photo: Apple orchard of W. S. Offner, circa 1900 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Photo: Asparagus picking and packing, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Photo: Attalia Project Supply Dam on Walla Walla River, circa 1909 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Photo: Baker-Langdon Orchard, looking toward Blue Mts., circa 1917 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Photo: Blalock Fruit Company, packing house and employees, circa 1913 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Photo: One section of the Blalock Ranch, circa 1905 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Photo: Field graded and sized onions in sacks, from the Bossini field, circa 1955 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Photo: Corn receiving area, Walla Walla, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Photo: Fort Nez Perce. From A. Ross' "Fur Hunters", Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Sketch: Residence of James W. Foster and surrounding area circa 1870s, Undated; Original and 1 photocopy (enlarged) (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Photo: Frazier apple tree, Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Photo: Apples from grafted Frazier apple tree grown on Locati's farm, Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Photo: Three trees grafted from Frazier apple tree, on Locati's farm, Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Photo: Frazier barn. Built in 1877, collapsed in 1982, Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Negatives: Frazier apple tree, circa 1978 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Photo: Prune warehouses at Garrett Siding; previously a unit of Blalock Fruit Co., Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Photo: Mechanical grape harvesting, Snake River Vineyards, circa 1976 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Photo: Hancock pear tree on site, 1981 August 25 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Photo: Grafted sapling from Hancock pear tree at Locati's farm, Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Photo: Pears from Locati's sapling, grafted from Hancock pear tree, Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Photo: "The Horticultural Heritage of Walla Walla County 1818-1977," publicity photos, Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Photo: Aerial view of circle irrigation near Snake River, circa 1977 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Photo: Chinese workers loading truck with sacks of onions, circa 1918 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Photo: Onions: Finishing a field, topping and filling field bins via field crates, Undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Photo: Onions: fall seeded onions in field, untreated for white rot, Undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Photo: Tarusci's onion field on Williams' place, Undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Photo: Onions in John Gao's field, circa 1977 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Photo: Orchard spraying demonstration in Walla Walla Valley, circa 1912 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Photo: Pasco Power and Water Co's irrigation project, circa 1909 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Photo: Pasco Power and Water Co., Wing Dam in Snake River, circa 1900 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Photo: Green pea viner station, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Photo: Pitchfork loading of green peas for processing, circa 1930 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Photo: Pioneer Park, circa 1977 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Photo: Seed potatoes, K2H farm, circa 1977 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Photo: Roadside stand, circa 1920 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Photo: Smith, W.D. Merchant; Lynum, Martin. Upholsterer. Alder between 1st and 2nd, circa 1887 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Photo: Giuseppe, Louis, Frank, and Royal Spagnuolo in onion field, circa 1915 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Photo: 4 row spinach cutter in field, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Photo: Home of Joseph Tachi, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Painting: Dave Manuel's Painting of the Whitman Mission House and Blacksmith Shop, Undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Photo: Walla Walla Gardeners' Association Packing Plant, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Photo: Walla Walla Produce Co. loading and unloading dock, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Photo: Walla Walla Produce Co. Prune Packinghouse stateline, Undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Photo: Joe Locati's Frazier apple tree, relocated to Whitman College, Undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Joe Locati: Clippings: Articles about The Horticultural Heritage of Walla Walla County, 1818-1977; letter to the editors of the Pacific Northwest Forum about Joe's articles, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Joe Locati: Correspondence with Walla Walla Union Bulletin (re: Article about Columbus); Ronald B. Tukey (Re: more copies of "The Horticultural Heritage"); Lawrence Dodd (Re: donations to archive collection); Berney family (Re: Locati's speech at William Berry's funeral), Undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Joe Locati: Article about "John Hancock" Pear Tree at Reavis Station, Undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Joe Locati: Research for article about John Hancock pear tree at Reavis Station: correspondence, etc., Undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Joe Locati: 11-part series, "Italian Jesuits in Northwest History". Written for the Walla Walla Italian Heritage News, Undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Joe Locati: Story about C.R. Frazier and his apple trees; article quoting Locati on ceremonial replanting of 3 Frazier trees, Undated (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Joe Locati: History of the "Whitman Campus" apple tree; 4 photos of said tree before 1972 removal; narrative of copyright issues between Locati and Larry McGraw, Undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Statue: Christopher Columbus. Article about Walla Walla Columbus Day celebrations; dedication of Columbus statue by Italian-American WW residents; full text of dedication speech by Father J.D. O'Brien; Joe Locati's article about history of Columbus Day in Walla Walla, Undated (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Article: "Columbus Quincentennial Snipes," by Joe Locati. Defense of Columbus' achievements in light of "recent Columbus-bashing", Undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
- Article: "Origin of the word 'wop'," by Joe Locati. Response to a Dear Abby column about the etymology of the derogatory term "wop", Undated (Box 1, Folder 57)
- "Walla Walla Sweet Onion: The French Connection" - excerpt from The Horticultural Heritage of Walla Walla County, 1818-1977 by Joe Locati, Undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
- History of Walla Walla horticulture: Two articles by Joe Locati, Undated (Box 1, Folder 59)
- Letter to the Editor of the Walla Walla Union Bulletin by Joe Locati Re: Misconceptions and errors in article entitled "Area's Italian-American history studied", 1989 May (Box 1, Folder 60)
- History of Giuseppe Tachi in Walla Walla, 1880 to 1912; Article in Walla Walla Union Bulletin re: Death of Joe Tachi, 1912; follow-up articles about his funeral and memorial service; article, "Men who have achieved success in the Walla Walla Valley" circa 1911. All compiled by Joe Locati, 1880-1912 (Box 1, Folder 61)
- Joe Locati: Newspaper Articles, Obituaries, and Funeral Announcement, 1982-1998 (Box 1, Folder 63)
- Newspaper clips regarding horticultural practices in Walla Walla, 1918-1981 (Box 2)